<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
     xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel>
  <title>(Emacs Debugging with Default Drop Firewall Policies and IPv6)</title>
  <atom:link href="https://kennyballou.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <link>https://kennyballou.com</link>
  <description><![CDATA[A rambling in self-inflicted suffering with Java, Emacs, DAP, and Firewalls!]]></description>
  <language>en</language>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 22:42:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 22:42:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
  <generator>Emacs 29.3 Org-mode 9.6.15</generator>
  <webMaster>kb@devnulllabs.io (kb)</webMaster>
  <image>
    <url>http://orgmode.org/img/org-mode-unicorn-logo.png</url>
    <title>(Emacs Debugging with Default Drop Firewall Policies and IPv6)</title>
    <link>https://kennyballou.com</link>
  </image>

  <div class="PREVIEW" id="orgb42b3bd">
    <p>
      Debugging <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/">Java</a> programs in <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> has been a goal and overall feature I have
      wanted for some time.  However, every time I've reached for it, <code>dap-java-debug</code>
      demonstrated an unbearably slow startup.  So much so, that it was often faster
      and more productive to launch <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ</a>, fight <a href="https://nixos.org/">Nix</a> and <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ</a> to load the
      project correctly, and launch the debugger from <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ</a>.
    </p>

    <p>
      No more.  The pain is gone, forced on by fighting <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ</a> to load one too many
      times.
    </p>

    <p>
      tl;dr: self-inflicted pain is a strange way to deeply learn.
    </p>

  </div>

  <p>
    Before programming took over, I wanted to be a security expert/red
    team/hacker.  This lead me to some strange places, one of which is the desire
    to <del>put hot glue in my Ethernet ports and disable WiFi</del> have strict firewall
    rules.  Specifically, default policy drop on all tables, including outbound.
  </p>

  <p>
    As a result of my current research, I've been predominately in <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/">Java</a> land.  I'm
    using <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> with <a href="https://langserver.org/">LSP</a> as my full-time <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/">Java</a> editor and it has not been without
    issue.  Although, it's been far more comfortable and reliable than the other
    two big IDE choices that exist (likely as a result of recursive suffering).
    That said, debugging <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/">Java</a> programs has been a non-starter with <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> and <a href="https://microsoft.github.io/debug-adapter-protocol/">DAP</a>.
    I could not explain why it would take more than 2 minutes to launch and connect
    to a debugging session facilitated by <a href="https://microsoft.github.io/debug-adapter-protocol/">DAP</a>.
  </p>
</channel>
</rss>
