<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
     xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel>
  <title>(Installing Guix (Full LUKS + LVM))</title>
  <atom:link href="https://kennyballou.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <link>https://kennyballou.com</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Installation Notes and Catches for installing a fully encrypted Guix include /boot on LUKS + LVM.]]></description>
  <language>en</language>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 23:46:43 +0000</pubDate>
  <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 23:46:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
  <generator>Emacs 29.3 Org-mode 9.6.15</generator>
  <webMaster>kb@devnulllabs.io (kb)</webMaster>
  <image>
    <url>http://orgmode.org/img/org-mode-unicorn-logo.png</url>
    <title>(Installing Guix (Full LUKS + LVM))</title>
    <link>https://kennyballou.com</link>
  </image>

  <div class="PREVIEW" id="orga665bd8">
    <p>
      Here are some notes about installing Guix SD onto a new system from an existing
      configuration.  We necessarily need to discuss disk preparation and
      partitioning.  Additionally, we discuss from the perspective of existing
      configurations.  I planned to write this back in 2022, after initially
      switching from NixOS to Guix.  I hesitated at the time since such a post would
      not have any additional value to people otherwise installing Guix.  However,
      going through the process again, I feel there are some comments to capture that
      may be beneficial to others venturing down this path.  I will save the
      discussion between NixOS and Guix for another time.  For now, let's settle on
      "scheme is more better."
    </p>

  </div>

  <p>
    After having a corrupted <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/grub">GRUB</a> kill my previous <a href="https://guix.gnu.org/">Guix System</a>, and a false sense
    of urgency, I have been running, begrudgingly, <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora Workstation</a> for the last
    10 months.  However, with summer here, I am eager to return to using <a href="https://guix.gnu.org/">Guix</a> as my
    primary OS.
  </p>

  <p>
    <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora</a> has been fine.  It seems to work for the most part.  But there just
    seems to be this constant encroaching entropy causing the system to become less
    and less stable.  Using <a href="https://guix.gnu.org/">Guix</a> as a package manager seemed to work fine in the
    beginning, but over time, it has started showing some degradation that is
    simply unworkable.  If I must scorch earth reinstall, I might as well install
    using my preferred OS and existing <a href="https://git.sr.ht/~kennyballou/dotfiles.git">system configuration</a>.  However, in my
    attempts to switch back to <a href="https://guix.gnu.org/">Guix</a>, I have uncovered some sharp edges, because of
    course.
  </p>
</channel>
</rss>
