<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
     xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel>
  <title>(Org Projects with Gantt Charts)</title>
  <atom:link href="https://kennyballou.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <link>https://kennyballou.com</link>
  <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
  <language>en</language>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:17:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:17:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
  <generator>Emacs 29.3 Org-mode 9.6.15</generator>
  <webMaster>kb@devnulllabs.io (kb)</webMaster>
  <image>
    <url>http://orgmode.org/img/org-mode-unicorn-logo.png</url>
    <title>(Org Projects with Gantt Charts)</title>
    <link>https://kennyballou.com</link>
  </image>

  <div class="PREVIEW" id="org2f6098f">
    <p>
      <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org-Mode</a> is a great way to store <code>TODO</code> items, store notes, and keep track of
      projects.  However, possibly due to ignorance of what is available, getting a
      concrete high-level view of a project is difficult.  There are numerous
      different visualizations that can be created to see the state of a project.
      Each answers a specific question, none are entirely complete.  Today, I have
      worked out a mechanism to generate <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gantt_chart">Gantt Charts</a> using <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Dynamic-Blocks.html">dynamic blocks</a> for a
      specific project tree.  In followup posts, I may work out some other
      visualizations.
    </p>

  </div>

  <p>
    <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Agenda-Views.html">Agenda</a> views can help gather and provide filtered projections of the <code>TODO</code> lists
    that comprise various projects.  But getting a holistic view of the progress is
    not entirely captured by <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Breaking-Down-Tasks.html">progress cookies</a> and <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Agenda-Views.html">agenda views</a>.  For example, a
    progress cookie cannot predict a project's completion because it lacks
    information about size of each task and estimated complexity of each task.  A
    project could be 98% complete, but the last 2% of tasks consist of 80% of the
    work necessary to complete.  Arguably, this is a failure in the project
    breakdown, but the point remains, some amount of tasks left over as a whole do
    not communicate the holistic progress and prediction towards completion.
  </p>
</channel>
</rss>
